A Finding Aid to the Emil Carlsen and Carlsen Family Photographs, circa 1885-circa 1930, in the Archives of American Art AAA.carlemil
Archives of American Art
Emil Carlsen and Carlsen family photographs
bulk 1910-1930
circa 1885-circa 1930
AAA.carlemil
Archives of American Art
1.6 Linear feet
The photographs of Emil Carlsen and the Carlsen family measure 1.6 linear feet and date from circa 1885 to circa 1930, with the bulk from circa 1910 to circa 1920s. Included in this collection are 169 glass plate negatives, black and white copy prints of all glass plate negatives, and four plastic safety negatives. Some descriptive annotations by Emil Carlsen are included.
Carlsen, Emil, 1853-1932
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Emil Carlsen and Carlsen family photographs were donated to the Archives of American Art on June 28, 1995, by Elizabeth M. Campanile of Campanile Galleries, Inc., which were purchased from the Dines Carlsen Estate.
Scope and Contents note
The photographs of Emil Carlsen and the Carlsen family measure 1.6 linear feet and date from circa 1885 to circa 1930, with the bulk from circa 1910 to circa 1920s. Included in this collection are 169 glass plate negatives, black and white copy prints of all glass plate negatives, and four plastic safety negatives. Some descriptive annotations by Emil Carlsen are included.
Also included are approximately 54 original glass plate negative sleeves containing contextual and descriptive information about the images penned by Emil Carlsen, which have been kept with their respective copy prints. Within the collection, 29 black and white copy prints and four plastic safety negatives were produced by the Smithsonian Archives of American Art from nitrate negatives no longer with the collection. Photographs include Emil Carlsen and his family, landscapes and animals, buildings and industrial exteriors, and artwork.
One third of the collection is made up of photographs of the artist and his family. Images of Emil Carlsen show the artist at work in his studio, painting outdoors, and enjoying time with his wife, Luella May Carlsen, and his son, Dines Carlsen. Also included are many photographs of Luella May and Dines over the years, alone and together. Additionally, Windham is listed as the town where several photographs of a very young Dines and Luella May were taken. The location of the rest of the photographs, when provided, is Port Washington.
Over half of the glass plate negatives depict landscapes, mostly of trees and various interiors and exteriors of the woods of Port Washington, New York. Landscape photographs also depict cornfields, a meadow, fences and roads, hills and mountains, boats and a marina, horses, and cattle.
Buildings and industrial exteriors contain multiple views of the exteriors of several houses and barns; cityscapes; a sand pit and quarry containing wooden building structures, equipment, and wagons.
Photographs of artwork include images of Emil Carlsen’s painted landscapes, still-lifes, a single self-portrait, and two seascapes.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
Biographical/Historical note
Painter Emil Carlsen (1853-1932) was born Soren Emil Carlsen in Copenhagen, Denmark in 1853. He studied architecture at the Danish Royal Academy for four years, and also painted alongside cousin and painter Viggo Johansen, one of Denmark’s most notable painters. In 1872, he immigrated to the United States where he worked as an architectural assistant and as an assistant for Danish marine painter Laurits Bernhard Holst (1848-1934) in Chicago, Illinois. After studying in Paris for several years, he set up a painting studio in New York and then Boston, then spending two years (1887-1889) as the Director of the San Francisco Arts Association School. In 1891, he moved back to New York and taught at the National Academy of Design until 1918. He spent most of his time with his family at their vacation home in Falls Village, Connecticut when he didn’t have teaching commitments in New York, where they also kept an apartment. In 1904, after struggling to become known for his work for many years, he was elected as an associate of the New York National Academy; he won the Shaw Prize from the Society of American Artists; and was awarded the Gold Medal at the 1904 World’s Fair in St. Louis for his still-life “Blackfish and Clams”. Carlsen is best known for his still-life paintings and has been called “The American Chardin.” Before purchasing his own property in Falls Village, Carlsen stayed often with friend and painter J. Alden Weir (1852-1919) at his farm, painting landscapes.
After deciding to make a career in painting rather than architectural design, Carlsen spent many years experimenting and finding his style. His paintings during 1872-1874 reflected his time spent assisting Laurits Bernhard Holst, and were in the style of traditional Danish marine paintings. Struggling financially, Holst arranged for Carlsen to receive his studio when Holst moved back to Denmark in 1874. At the recommendation of Chicago sculptor Leonard Wells Volk, Carlsen became an art instructor at the now Chicago Arts Institute, though he left for an opportunity to study classical painting for 6 months in Paris, where he spent time studying the painting of Jean-Baptiste-Simeon Chardin.
After Paris, he moved to a boarding house in New York, and then spent several years in Boston where he had his first exhibit at the Boston Art Club. In 1879 he moved back to New York and set up a studio, supplementing his painting with work as an engraver. During the 1880s Carlsen began becoming known for his still-life paintings, and commission work sent him to Paris again, this time for two years. He was commissioned by T. J. Blakeslee to produce bright flower paintings which were popular at the time, creating about one per month. Other American dealers began wanting his flower paintings as well, but Carlsen soon grew bored and returned to New York, refusing to paint any more flowers for Blakeslee, in 1887. It was during this time that Carlsen developed an interest in still-lifes with Chinese porcelain. His time in Paris also saw a brightening of his landscapes, as was the European style of the time. In the late 1800s he also became interested in painting white objects, such as porcelain, ceramics, garlic cloves, clothing, etc.
He married Luella May Ruby, a young model, in 1896, and his son Dines Carlsen was born in 1901. From 1900-1932, Carlsen favored a subdued color palette in his work. As still-life paintings fell out of vogue, he also painted more landscapes and marines, favoring Falls Village, Connecticut; Windham, Maine; and Port Washington, New York.
He died in New York at the age of 78, in 1932.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 5 series. Glass plate negatives are housed separately, but a cross reference number has been provided to match copy prints with with their respective glass plate negative original.
Series 1: Photographs of People, circa 1890s-circa 1920s (0.5 linear feet; Boxes 1, 3-4)
Series 2: Photographs of Buildings and Industrial Exteriors, circa 1885-circa 1930 (0.2 linear feet; Boxes 1, 3-4)
Series 3: Photographs of Landscapes and Animals, circa 1885-circa 1930 (0.5 linear feet; Boxes 1-4)
Series 4: Photographs of Artwork, circa 1885-circa 1930 (0.4 linear feet; Boxes 2-4)
Series 5: Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1920s (1 folder; Box 2)
Carlsen, Dines; Carlsen, Luella May; Artists at or with their work; Artists' studios-Photographs; Copy prints; Glass plate negatives ##local; Photographs
- Photographs of People, circa 1890s-circa 1920s; Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 1, 3-4
  Scope and Contents note
  Included here are photographs of Emil Carlsen and his wife, Luella May Carlsen, and son, Dines Carlsen, though the bulk of the series contains photographs of Luella May and Dines, together and individually. Several photographs capture Emil with Dines as a baby; posed in his studio; painting on a rocky seaside using a travel easel/painting kit; and sitting on or near several trees in open fields.
  Luella May Carlsen has been photographed over the course of about 30 years, and is depicted sitting and standing in the woods and indoors, both alone and with Dines. One candid photograph shows Dines and Luella May lost to smiles and laughter. There are also several portrait shots of Luella May wrapped in a blanket and robe, some with a small bird perched on her shoulder. The earliest image of Luella May is noted as "Mrs. C, dark corner," in which she appears to be about to walk away while casting a sideways glance at the camera, standing in a living or dining room.
  Photographs of Emil Carlsen’s son, Dines Carlsen, have been taken over the span of 15 to 20 years, from a baby to a young man, both with his mother and alone, playing, painting, and laughing. Only two photographs circa 1915 (taken from damaged glass plate negatives) show the whole family together indoors next to a large framed painting, with Emil sitting in an overstuffed chair, looking at the painting, and Dines and Luella May standing behind him – the photograph appears to have been taken from just outside a doorway. Also included are three images of an unidentified boy, possibly Dines Carlsen, as well as an unidentified man.
  Researchers should note that descriptive annotations taken verbatim from glass plate sleeves are in quotes. Also, photographs are described largely by groups, and some photograph descriptions have been added for clarity.
  Arrangement note
  Photographs are arranged by subject. Glass plate negatives are housed separately, but a cross reference number has been provided to match copy prints with with their respective glass plate negative original.
  - Emil Carlsen, circa 1905-circa 1908; 3 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 1)
    "E. C. in field"
    "E. C. under apple tree, Port Washington"
    In front of tree
  - Emil Carlsen Posed in Studio, circa 1920; 4 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Emil Carlsen, circa 1920s; 3 Copy prints Prints taken from nitrate negatives (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Sitting on tree
    Painting at seaside
  - Emil Carlsen Painting at Seaside, circa 1920s; 1 Negatives (photographic) Safety negative taken from nitrate negatives (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Emil and Dines Carlsen, circa 1902; 3 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "E. C. and D. C."
    "E. C. and D. C. with ball"
  - Emil, Luella May, and Dines Carlsen, circa 1915; 2 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Luella May and Dines Carlsen, circa 1901; 1 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Luella May and Dines Carlsen, Port Washington, circa 1902; 2 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 8)
    "M. C. and D. C."
    "D. C. and M. C., blurred, Port Washington"
  - Luella May and Dines Carlsen, Windham, circa 1906; 1 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 9)
    "M. C. and D. C., Windham"
  - Luella May and Dines Carlsen Laughing, circa 1909; 1 Copy prints Prints taken from nitrate negatives (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Luella May and Dines Carlsen in Woods, circa 1909; 2 Copy prints Prints taken from nitrate negatives (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Luella May and Dines Carlsen, circa 1909; 2 Copy prints Prints taken from nitrate negatives (Box 1, Folder 12)
    With boats
    Looking in window
  - Luella May and Dines Carlsen with Boats, circa 1909; 1 Negatives (photographic) Safety negative taken from nitrate negatives (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Luella May and Dines Carlsen at Seaside, circa 1917; 1 Copy prints Prints taken from nitrate negatives (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Dines Carlsen, with Dah, circa 1901; 2 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 15)
    "Dah and D. C."
    "Dah and D. C., Port Washington"
  - Dines Carlsen, circa 1902-circa 1904; 2 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 16)
    "D. C. in long clothes"
    "D. C. sitting on wall, Windham"
  - Dines Carlsen Portrait, circa 1909; 2 Copy prints Prints taken from nitrate negatives (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Dines Carlsen in City Feeding Pigeons, circa 1909; 1 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Dines Carlsen in City Playing Tennis, circa 1910; 2 Copy prints Prints taken from nitrate negatives (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Dines Carlsen Indoors, circa 1917; 3 Copy prints Prints taken from nitrate negatives (Box 1, Folder 20)
    In front of screen
    With camera
  - Dines Carlsen Indoors with Camera, circa 1917; 1 Negatives (photographic) Safety negative taken from nitrate negatives (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Luella May Carlsen, circa 1890s; 2 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 22)
    "Mrs. C. dark corner"
    "Mrs. C. in field, Port Washington"
  - Luella May Carlsen in Woods, circa 1904; 2 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 23)
    "M. C. in wood interior, Port Washington"
    "M. C. in woods"
  - Luella May Carlsen, circa 1906; 1 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 24)
    "M. C., full length, Port Washington"
  - Luella May Carlsen, circa 1906; 2 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 25)
    "M. C. in grass under oak, Port Washington"
    "M. C. under oak"
  - Luella May Carlsen in Woods, circa 1912; 4 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Luella May Carlsen, circa 1920s; 6 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Portrait in studio with bird
    With car
    At seaside
  - Luella May Carlsen, circa 1920s; 6 Copy prints Prints taken from nitrate negatives (Box 1, Folder 28)
    In robe and blanket, indoors
  - Luella May Carlsen, circa 1920s; 2 Copy prints Prints taken from nitrate negatives (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Sitting in the woods
  - Unidentified Boy, circa 1910s; 3 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 30)
    "Boy on horse, Port Washington"
    "Oak in wood with boy"
  - Unidentified Man, circa 1910s; 1 Copy prints Prints taken from nitrate negatives (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Glass Plate Negatives, circa 1890s-circa 1920s; 41 Glass negatives (Box 3-4)
- Photographs of Buildings and Industrial Exteriors, circa 1885-circa 1930; Series 2; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 1, 3-4
  Included here are photographs of old houses and barns, as well as several of industrialized sand pits/quarry and cityscapes depicting different levels of construction and building, probably in New York City where the Carlsen’s lived.
  Researchers should note that descriptive annotations in quotes were taken verbatim from glass plate sleeves.
  - Old House, circa 1885-circa 1930; 2 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 32)
    "Old House with corn stalks"
    "Old Barn, Port Washington"
  - House, Exteriors, circa 1885-circa 1930; 5 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - House, Exterior, circa 1885-circa 1930; 1 Copy prints Prints taken from nitrate negatives (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Old Barn, Port Washington, circa 1885-circa 1930; 2 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Stone Crusher and Quarry, circa 1885-circa 1930; 2 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Sand Pit, circa 1885-circa 1930; 2 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 37)
    "Sand pit, Port Washington"
    "Wagon in sand pit"
  - Cityscapes, Construction, circa 1885-circa 1930; 3 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Glass Plate Negatives, circa 1885-circa 1930; 16 Glass negatives (Box 3-4)
- Photographs of Landscapes and Animals, circa 1885-circa 1930; Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 1-4
  Found here are images of varying landscapes, though most depict trees and woods. Port Washington is noted as the primary location of the landscape photographs of pastures with cattle and horses, cornfields, meadows, and boats/marinas. Also here are images of landscapes with rolling hills and mountains with large, expansive skies, as well as a couple of images of woods surrounding waterfalls.
  - Cattle, Port Washington, circa 1885-circa 1930; 2 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 39)
    "Cattle, Port Washington"
    "Young bull, Port Washington"
  - Cattle, Port Washington, circa 1885-circa 1930; 2 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 40)
    "Cattle in pasture, Port Washington"
    "Cow lying in field, Port Washington"
  - Horses, circa 1885-circa 1930; 2 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 41)
    "Team and wagon (double exposure) P. W."
    "Road with buggy, Port Washington"
  - Boats, Port Washington, circa 1885-circa 1930; 4 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Roads and Fences, circa 1885-circa 1930; 3 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Hills and Mountains, circa 1885-circa 1930; 5 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Hills and Mountains with Cloud-Filled Skies, circa 1885-circa 1930; 12 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Meadow and Field, Port Washington, circa 1885-circa 1930; 2 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Cornfields, Port Washington, circa 1885-circa 1930; 4 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 47)
    "Cornfield with oak, Port Washington"
    "Landscape with shocks - P. W."
    "Landscape with cornshocks"
    "Corn shucks, Port Washington"
  - Landscape with House/Barn, circa 1885-circa 1930; 4 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Clouds with Trees and Powerlines, circa 1885-circa 1930; 1 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Trees, Port Washington, circa 1885-circa 1930; 3 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 50)
    "Oaks by river bank, Port Washington"
    "Apple tree stump, Port Washington"
  - Elm in Field, Port Washington, circa 1885-circa 1930; 2 Copy prints (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Oak Trees, Port Washington, circa 1885-circa 1930; 4 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Woods, Exterior, circa 1885-circa 1930; 2 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Woods, Interior, circa 1885-circa 1930; 26 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 3-6)
    "Woods, interior, Port Washington"
  - Woods, Waterfalls, circa 1885-circa 1930; 2 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Glass Plate Negatives, circa 1885-circa 1930; 79 Glass negatives (Box 3-4)
- Photographs of Artwork, circa 1885-circa 1930; Series 4; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 2-4
  Included here are photographs of primarily Emil Carlsen's paintings of still-lifes and landscapes, with one photograph of a still-life composition later painted by Emil. Also included are one image of a still-life signed and dated by Dines Carlsen, and one image of a landscape by painter J. Alden Weir.
  Emil Carlsen’s son, Dines Carlsen, learned to paint from his father, and both spent time painting in the same studio. As a result, Dines’ paintings mimic Emil’s style, making unsigned works difficult to identify. In this collection, there are several photographs of undated landscape paintings by an unidentified artist, though probably painted by either Dines or Emil Carlsen.
  Researchers should note that descriptive annotations in quotes were taken verbatim from glass plate sleeves. Also, photographs are described largely by groups, and some photograph descriptions have been added for clarity.
  - Painting by Emil Carlsen, Self Portrait, circa 1890s; 1 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 8)
    "E. C.'s self portrait (holding glass)"
  - Paintings by Emil Carlsen, Landscapes and Flowers, circa 1885-1895; 3 Copy prints Prints taken from nitrate negatives (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Paintings by Emil Carlsen, Still Life, circa 1894; 1 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 10)
    'Still Life with Swan'
  - Paintings by Emil Carlsen, Still Life, circa 1890s; 3 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Paintings by Emil Carlsen, Still Life, 1920; 1 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 12)
    'The Leeds Jug'
  - Paintings by Emil Carlsen, Still Life, 1926-1929; 5 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Still Life Composition, circa 1929; 1 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Paintings by Emil Carlsen, Landscapes, circa 1920s; 3 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Paintings by Emil Carlsen, Seascapes, circa 1928; 4 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Paintings by Emil Carlsen, Landscapes, 1928; 4 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Landscape with bridge
    Landscape with waterfall
  - Paintings by Emil Carlsen, Landscapes, circa 1929-circa 1930; 4 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Landscape with horse and cows
    'Wood Pasture'
  - Paintings by Emil Carlsen, Allegorical Landscape, circa 1930; 2 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Painting by J. Alden Weir, Landscape, circa 1908; 2 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Painting by Dines Carlsen, Still Life, 1928; 2 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Paintings, Landscapes, Artist Unidentified, circa 1915-circa 1925; 5 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Painting, Still Life, Artist Unidentified, circa 1915-circa 1925; 2 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Paintings, Landscapes in Woods, Artist Unidentified, circa 1915-circa 1925; 4 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Paintings, Landscapes with Luella May Carlsen, Artist Unidentified, circa 1915-circa 1925; 4 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Glass Plate Negatives, circa 1885-circa 1930; 33 Glass negatives (Box 3-4)
- Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1920s; Series 5; 1 Folders Box 2
  Found here is one unmatched glass plate negative sleeve with notes and annotations.
  - Annotated Photonegative Sleeve, circa 1920s (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Materials are arranged by subject.